Finding Aid for Karl L. Zinn papers, 1964-1997
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Karl L. Zinn papers 1964-1997
Zinn, Karl L.
20 linear feet
0476 Aa2
Karl L. Zinn, a specialist in computer-assisted instruction, joined the University of Michigan faculty in 1963 as a research associate with the Center for Research on Learning and Teaching. Promoted to research scientist in 1969, Zinn was instrumental in establishing the MERIT computer network and developing CONFER, the first computer-based conferencing systems on campus. Papers document the development and utilization of CONFER and contain extensive examples of print-outs of conferences, particularly those relating to the use of computers in instruction. Topical files chronicle various technological issues, including the development of MERIT and early uses of computers in the classroom.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The papers (donor no. 9437 ) were received in 2001.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research with the exception of some student educational material closed under the Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act.
The Zinn papers include restricted material in the following categories:
Student Academic Records -- Boxes 12-13
Karl L. Zinn joined the University of Michigan faculty in 1963 as a research associate in the Center for Research on Learning and Teaching (CRLT) and as a lecturer in psychology. Zinn was promoted to research scientist in 1969 and maintained this title until he retired from active faculty status in 1997. Zinn joined the Information Technology Division in 1995.
Zinn received his B.A. degree from Swarthmore College in 1959 and his M.A. and Ph.D. degrees from the University of Michigan in 1962 and 1964, respectively. Zinn's first work assignment in CRLT was to assist faculty with problems related to testing and evaluation of computer technology for classroom use. Zinns work in this area soon led to him being identified as one of the "best informed individuals in America in the area of computer-assisted instruction, establishing connections with other research centers and setting up demonstration projects using access to the experimental computer systems at IBM, Dartmouth and the University of Illinois."[1] Other significant accomplishments include writing a proposal to the State of Michigan for a possible shared information network to be used among major universities. This proposal resulted in a planning grant for a state-wide computing network. Zinn also authored the proposal to the National Science Foundations that led to the development of the MERIT (Michigan Education and Research Information Triad) computer network in 1966. Zinn was named an associate director of MERIT in 1969.[2]
Zinn is also credited for introducing computer graphics to the University of Michigan; putting the first interactive programming language on the Michigan Terminal System; programming simulations and academic games for instruction; and setting up the first computer-based conferencing system, CONFER, on campus.[3]
CONFER was developed in the mid-1970s when experimental psychology graduate student Bob Parnes attended a seminar which Professor Merrill Flood discussed aspects of electronic mail and conferencing on group decision making. Professor Flood had a prototype of such a program and approached Parnes to modify the application for MTS but, Parnes was interested in developing a program from the ground up.[4] With the support of the University, particularly the Center for Research on Learning and Teaching, CONFER was developed.
Parnes' vision of the system was one where the individual group participant would alternate between being a producer and being a consumer of information. The unique CONFER feature in this regard was initially the functionality of the "vote." This feature allowed the consumer to voice their "feelings" or opinion on a statement by voting. Initially, responses were limited in size.
The first major "test" for the CONFER system was the October 1976 International Society for Technology Assessment (ISTA) Conference held in Ann Arbor. Zinn was interested in testing the technology to facilitate the coordination of tasks among the conference staff as well as using the system to allow conference participants to extend discussions on conference topics. CONFER provided a new opportunity for group discussion and is credited for playing a "tremendous role in enlarging the electronic community" at the University of Michigan.[5]
CONFER continued to gain in popularity with faculty, students, administrators and staff through the 1980s. By 1991, a group of students established the first computer conference for exclusively for students called MEET: STUDENTS. This very popular conference marked, in a sense, the acceptance of online communications as a culturally accepted mode for student communication and exchange.
For many on campus, the benefits of CONFER included meeting new people with similar interests, engaging in group discussion, and communicating outside the normal parameters defined by time and space. The CONFER system continued to be a widely used communication tool until 1999. By this time, the university had moved from the Michigan Terminal System to a distributed computing environment and several newer digital technologies replaced the functionality provided by CONFER. [6]
_____________________________________
NOTES
1) Information taken from University of Michigan Regent’s Proceedings, January Meeting, 1998.
2) Eric M. Aupperle, Merit—Who, What, and Why Part One: The Early Years, 1964-1983, Merit Network, Inc., website, http://www.merit.edu (last viewed September 14, 2004).
3)Information taken from University of Michigan Regent’s Proceedings, January Meeting, 1998
4) MTS Fostered Creation of Computing Community, Information Technology Digest, May 13, 1996 (vol. 5, no. 5).
5) Susan E. Topol, Students Met Students on Confer U, InfoTech Digital, September 8, 1997.
6) ibid.
The Karl Zinn papers document the development and utilization of CONFER, the first computer-based conferencing system on campus, and contain extensive examples of print-outs of conferences, particularly those relating to the use of computers in instruction. Topical files chronicle various technological issues, including the development of MERIT, the Michigan state-wide computer network, and early uses of computers in the classroom. The Zinn papers are organized into three series CONFER, Topical Files and User Reference Documentation.
Subjects:
Computer assisted instruction.; Computer networks--Michigan.; Computer conferencing--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Information technology.; MERIT Computer Network.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
- CONFER
  The CONFER series provides documentation on of the development and use of the CONFER software at the University of Michigan. (14 linear feet, 1975-1991) is comprised of two subseries: Background Material, and CONFER Sessions.
  - Background Material
    Background materials include Robert Parnes' dissertation Learning to CONFER: The Interplay of Theory and Practice in Computer Conferencing, "A Call for a Conference Topic" by Parnes and a CONFER printout titled " How to Get the Most from the Least: Some Thoughts on Microcomputers in Education" written by Karl Zinn.
    - Agenda for CRLT (Center for Research on Learning and Teaching): Research and Development September 12, 1979 (Box 1)
    - Dissertation Learning to CONFER: The Interplay of Theory and Practice in Computer Conferencing, Robert Parnes, 1981, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - How to Get the Most from the Least: Some Thoughts on Microcomputers in Education Karl Zinn, September 15, 1978 (Box 1)
    - Introduction: Call for a Conference Topic Robert Parnes, April 15, 1975 (oversized printout) (Box 1)
    - Model for Teleconferencing, Karl Zinn, March 24, 1975 (Box 1)
    - What is Computer Conferencing, CONFER.QUEST April 20, 1979 (Box 1)
  - CONFER Sessions
    The CONFER Sessions subseries is comprised of paper printouts from a subset of computer-based conferences that ran on the University of Michigan mainframe computing system (Michigan Terminal System) from 1975 to 1994. These were printed by Zinn, and are indicative of his involvement and interests. This subseries provides an informative view of the introduction, evolution and use of a new technology designed specifically to support computer-based communications. The subseries includes RP.CONFER the original conference that utilized the CONFER I application program; student administered conferences; conferences used to supplement class discussion; and a series of conferences designed for the International Science and Technology Assessment Congress held in Ann Arbor in 1976. The CONFER Sessions subseries is divided into Public Conferences and University of Michigan Class Conferences. Access to the latter is restricted in accord with the Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act.
    The CONFER paper printouts are essentially a static snapshot of an asynchronous communications system. The term "snapshot" is used as the original functionality of the CONFER II system are features that could not be replicated in the paper printouts. In addition, not all entries, once posted within the system, could be captured in the paper printout as some entries were time-dependent and were deleted on a specific schedule. Lastly, the interactive nature of CONFER can not be adequately captured in a static document. As Zinn describes in a welcome message, literally "hundreds of participants passed by this electronic bulletin board from day to day."7 A sense of the features and the evolution of the use and functionality of the system can be gained by consulting the User Reference Documentation series and Robert Parnes' dissertation. The features and use of the technology can also be realized through some of the CONFERS themselves. Robert Parnes used CONFER as a testbed and one will often see Parnes "step" into a particular session to query users about the functionality of specific features and to announce changes to the system.
    CONFER printouts are available in two sizes. For the most part, conferences dating from 1975 to about 1980 were printed on 15" x 11" paper, and conferences dating after 1980 were printed on standard 8 1/2" x 11" paper. For the larger sized conferences, the cover sheet of the printout includes the job number that produced the conference report, the system source, and the date and time the report was generated. Later printouts do not include all of this information but do include the date the session was printed to paper.
    Entries within conferences generally include the item number, date and time, number of lines for a particular entry, author, subject line and a calculation of the number of related items on this topic within the conference. Many of the conferences include an index of topics discussed and a directory of participants. The index is generally found at the start of the conference and the directory of participants at the end. In addition, many conferences also include as one of the first entries a welcome message from the conference organizer that includes a brief description of the purpose of the conference. CONFER II and later CONFER U were in use at the University of Michigan from 1975 until September 1, 1999. A summary of the CONFER sessions located in this collection appears below.
    [Sources: CRLT:MICROS, Volume IV, A snapshot of dialogue on microcomputers in education, ca. October 1983 and USER:FORUM, Recent changes to Confer, Item 6, 05:09 Sep08/82, posted by Bob Parnes.]
    - Public Conferences 1975-circa 1980
      - Activity Report 1977 (Box 1)
      - CAP: SHARE August 1976-June 1977, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - CAP: WAR 1976-1977 (Box 1)
      - CAP: SUMMER June-July 1978 (Box 1)
      - CONFER, List of Conferences at the University of Michigan 1976-1977 (Box 1)
      - CONFER II, User's Guide, August 31,1977 (Box 1)
      - CRLT: G804 January-April 1979 (oversized printout) (Box 1)
      - CRLT: Conference, Listing of Descriptors and Items circa 1975 (oversized printout) (Box 1)
      - CRLT: Conference September 1976-April 1977 (Box 1)
        (oversized printout)
      - 2G2B: Staff January-April 1993 (Box 2)
      - AIGP: Forum (Artificial Intelligence) March 1983-1987, 3 folders (Box 2)
      - ARCH: Forum November 1986-April 1987 (Box 2)
      - CABA: Micro-Ed February 1984, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - CAUCUS January-April 1976 (Box 2)
      - CPS: Word (CONFER Problems and Suggestions) February 1983-January 1984, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - GRAF: Graphics November 1977-March 1989 (Box 2)
      - IEAR: Advisors, (Advisory services for computers in education) December 1982-April 1983 (Box 2)
      - LINK: ART April 1987-June 1988 (Box 2)
      - LISA-MAC April-April 1984, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - LOGO: Forum May 1985-April 1987 (Box 2)
      - MICH: EIC, (Michigan Effective Instruction Consortium) December 1988-June 1989 (Box 2)
      - MICH: GIFTEd August 1989 (Box 2)
      - MICH: SPEDTEC November 1985 (Box 2)
      - MCUL: CURE September-December 1986 (Box 2)
      - MCUL: Forum January 1988-May 1989 (Box 2)
      - MCUL: SIGCC April 1986-May 1989 (Box 2)
      - MSTA: Forum (Michigan Science Teachers Association)
        - February 1985-April 1987 (Box 2)
        - January-August 1989 (Box 2)
      - NETI: Forum August 1984 (Box 2)
      - NETI: Staff August 1984 (Box 2)
      - PC2:!Conf June 1986-April 1987 (Box 2)
      - RC: FoodSupply (Residential College) January-March 1987 (Box 2)
      - Religion September-November 1987 (Box 2)
      - RP.CONFER (Robert Parnes) June-July 1975 (Box 2)
      - Span: MS (MicroSpan) March-July 1982 (Box 2)
      - Span: Vision April-May 1990 (Box 2)
      - K556: OLDMAGNA March 1977-March 1978 (Box 3)
      - CRLT: CON.Ed February-May 1979 (Box 3)
      - CRLT: CONF July 1975-July 1976, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - CRLT: Conduit February-April 1976 (Box 3)
      - CRLT: Planning September-March 1979 (Box 3)
      - MICROS February-May 1978 (Box 3)
      - MNET: CAUCUS
        - August-October 1978 (Box 3)
        - August 1978-January 1980, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - RP CONFER April-September 1975 (Box 3)
      - STST:Con.CENSUS
        - February-April 1976 (Box 3)
        - May 1976-June 1977 (Box 3)
      - SPSS: Talk June 1976-June 1977 (Box 3)
      - Untitled May 1975 (Box 3)
      - Untitled, possibly Micros May 1978-May 1980 (Box 3)
      - Untitled February-December 1979, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - CRLT: Advisors December 1982-October 1983, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - CRLT: AUC July-August 1984 (Box 4)
      - CRLT: CBE (Computer Based Education) October 1975-March 1976 (Box 4)
      - CRLT: EdMicro
        - Volume I August 1984-September 1985 (Box 4)
        - Volume II October 1985-January 1989 (Box 4)
      - CRLT: Expos September-December 1986 (Box 4)
      - CRLT: HC March-May 1988 (Box 4)
      - CRLT: Hypercard April 1988-November 1991 (Box 4)
      - CRLT: Learning September-November 1986 (Box 4)
      - CRLT: LT January-March 1986 (Box 4)
      - CRLT: MAC.NOTES (Box 5)
        - March-June 1984 (Box 5)
        - August 1984-September 1985, 2 folders (Box 5)
        - October 1985-March 1987, 3 folders (Box 5)
        - March 1987-November 1989, 3 folders (Box 5)
      - CRLT: MERRA November 1976 (Box 5)
      - CRLT: MICROS
        - Volume III June 1980-June 1981, 3 folders (Box 5)
        - Volume IV January-September 1983, 2 folders (Box 5)
        - Volume V September 1983-July 1984, 3 folders (Box 5)
        - Volume VI August 1984-June 1985, 3 folders (Box 5)
        - Volume VII July-March 1986, 10 folders (Box 6)
        - Volume VIII March 1986-June 1987, 6 folders (Box 6)
        - Volume IX July 1987-December 1989, 8 folders (Box 7)
      - CRLT: Musiccomp October-November 1986 (Box 7)
      - CRLT: OldMicros October 1981-December 1982, 2 folders (Box 7)
      - CRLT: Peace January-April 1986 (Box 8)
      - CRLT: Organizer September 1978-April 1987, 3 folders (Box 8)
      - CRLT: RELIGION January-April 1988, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - CRLT: Staff July 1981-June 1983, 4 folders (Box 8)
      - CRLT: TA
        - April 1988-April 1989 (Box 8)
        - February-July 1991 (Box 8)
      - CRLT: Teachers April-June 1983 (Box 8)
      - CRLT: QUEST February 1986 (Box 8)
      - CRLT: UBMAC October 1985-September 1988 (Box 8)
      - CRLT: USE.CONFER
        - March 1986-February 1987 (Box 8)
        - February 1988-April 1990 (Box 8)
      - CRLT: Use.CONFER1, December 1985-Feburary 1986 (Box 8)
      - CRLT: WS351
        - January-March 1987, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - CRLT: WORDP, March 1 1979-June 1981, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - Second International Congress on Technology Assessment, sponsored by International Society for Technology Assessment (ISTA) Conference October 24-28, 1976 (Box 9)
        - ISTA: AGRICULTURE October 1976 (Box 9)
        - ISTA: ASPECTS October 1976 (Box 9)
        - ISTA: DEVELOPMENT October 1976 (Box 9)
        - ISTA: EDUCATION October 1976 (Box 9)
        - ISTA: GLOSSARY October 1976 (Box 9)
        - ISTA: MICRO February-March 1977 (Box 9)
        - ISTA: PARADIGMS October 1976 (Box 9)
        - ISTA: PERSPECTIVES October 1976 (Box 9)
        - ISTA: PLANNING (background staff communications) October 1976 (Box 9)
        - ISTA: PROJECTS October 1976 (Box 9)
        - ISTA: SCHEDULE October 1976 (Box 9)
        - ISTA: SOLAR, October 1976-Feburary 1977 (Box 9)
        - ISTA: STAFF October 1976 (Box 9)
        - ISTA: WRITINGS October 1976 (Box 9)
      - MEET: OURSELVES May-December 1986, 3 folders (Box 10)
      - MEET: PLANNERS April 1985-December 1986, 3 folders (Box 10)
        (originally started as LBFM: SAMPLE)
      - MEET: STUDENTS
        - Volume I September 1985 (index) (Box 10)
        - Volume II September-November 1986, 3 folders (Box 10)
      - MEET: UM
        - August-November 1986, 2 folders (Box 10)
        - January-September 1988 (Box 10)
      - MNET: CAUCUS, Volume IV August 1980-June 1981 (Box 10)
      - NOW: CONSIDER March-September 1989 (Box 10)
      - STAT: Con.Census, (background materials only) circa 1976 (Box 10)
      - UMED: MEDNET, (index only) November 1987 (Box 11)
      - User: UB April-September 1985 (Box 11)
      - USER: FORUM
        - Volume I, started May 1979 (Box 11)
        - Volume II July 1980-September 1981, 3 folders (Box 11)
        - Volume III September 1982-June 1983, 2 folders (Box 11)
        - Volume IV September 1985-September 1988, 2 folders (Box 11)
      - User: OldForum, Volume 3 September 1981-April 1992, 2 folders (Box 11)
      - USER Planning January 1980-March 1981, 2 folders (Box 11)
    - University of Michigan Class Conferences circa 1978-1992
      - 1CVA: Wonderland September-October 1987 (Box 12)
        [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2062 ]
      - 1GDB: CS181 September-December 1992, 2 folders (Box 12)
        [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2067 ]
      - 1GHA: Writing September-December 1986, 2 folders (Box 12)
        [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2061 ]
      - 1JYA: 503 September-December 1986-1987 (Box 12)
        [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2052 ]
      - 1J3A: PEACE September-October 1985 (Box 12)
        [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2060 ]
      - 2GDA: Comp74 January-April 1987, 2 folders (Box 12)
        [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2053 ]
      - 2G2B: 181 CONFER January-April 1992 (Box 12)
      - 2KSB: 181 CONFER January-April 1992, 2 folders (Box 12)
      - 2Q1A: Argue February-April 1986, 2 folders (Box 12)
      - BAD: IDEA March-September 1986 (Box 12)
      - GULF: FORUM March-May 1991 (Box 12)
        [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2066 ]
      - K9JK: UTEPSEM September-December 1986 (Box 12)
        [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2051 ]
      - Linguistics and Computers December 1986 (Box 12)
      - MAYA: PEACE September-December 1985 (Box 12)
      - Professional Composer circa 1987 (Box 12)
        [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2062 }
      - RC.Community
        - October -- November 1986 (Box 12)
        - September-November 1988 (Box 12)
          [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2063 ]
      - RC: WIN 86H445 January-May 1986 (Box 12)
      - 5B2A:N830, School of Nursing January-July 1979 (Box 13)
        [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2054 ]
      - LAW 814
        - September-December 1978, 2 folders (Box 13)
        - September-December 1979 (Box 13)
      - N630, School of Nursing January-March 1976 (Box 13)
      - SSHD, School of Nursing January-May 1976 (Box 13)
- Topical Files
  The Topical Files series (6 linear feet, 1964-1997) includes a substantial amount of information on MERIT, MICIS (Michigan Inter-University Committee on Information Systems), Project EXTEND (Extending University Computing Resources into College Learning Activities) and the University Committee on Computer Policy and Utilization (UCCPU). The files in this series are arranged alphabetically. In addition, the subseries is valuable for the range of grant proposals, reports and other initiatives Zinn was involved in during this time period to learn about and integrate the use of microcomputers in education. Zinn includes additional context for many of the project files found within this series by his use of "notes" to the file. These notes, generally hand-written, are typically the first document located within a file.
  - AAAS (American Association for the Advancement of Science) Workshop June-July 1975 (Box 14)
  - Academic Computing Policy Subcommittee February 1985 (Box 14)
  - Ann Arbor Public Schools, demonstration of Computer Aided Instruction (CAI) undated (Box 14)
  - Author-Training Proposal circa 1967 (Box 14)
  - Bell Telephone Systems circa 1965 (Box 14)
  - Bell Telephone Laboratories circa 1969 (Box 14)
  - CAI (Computer Assisted Instruction) circa 1966
    - Demonstration materials June 1966 (Box 14)
    - Proposal Project 1965 (Box 14)
  - Computer-based educational communications at the University of Michigan circa 1976 (Box 14)
  - Computing Center
    - Internal Memorandums August 1973-March 1980, 3 folders (Box 14)
  - Computing Materials 1972-1974
    - Dearborn (Box 14)
    - Flint (Box 14)
    - Oakland University (Box 14)
    - Wayne State University (Box 14)
    - Western Michigan University (Box 14)
  - Computer Sourcebook, background material circa 1973 (Box 14)
  - CONCOMP (Research in the Conversational Use of Computers)
    - General 1968-1981, 2 folders (Box 14)
    - Instruction circa 1967 (Box 14)
    - Memorandum PDP-8 Simulator July 1967 (Box 14)
    - Progress Reports circa 1967 (Box 14)
  - Computers in Instruction Conference October 1-3, 1970 (Box 14)
  - Conferences, general 1975 (Box 14)
  - Conferences Lists of Topics and Potential Participants 1976 (Box 14)
  - Conference on Instructional Computing in Michigan (ICM) March 1973 (Box 14)
  - Correspondence
    - Robben Fleming February 1974 (Box 14)
    - Ted Glaser May 1, 1972 (Box 14)
    - (Related to) Sourcebook on Resource Sharing for Instructional Computing circa 1974 (Box 14)
  - Educom, EST pilot undated (Box 14)
  - Educom Conference October 1972 (Box 14)
  - EXPERIM (Experimental Simulation) 1976 (Box 14)
  - Exxon Proposal circa 1971 (Box 14)
  - Flyers, computing events circa 1975 (Box 15)
  - Grant proposal, Languages and Technical Assistance circa 1970 (Box 15)
  - INFONET, Educom Conference held in Ann Arbor, Michigan 1989 (Box 15)
  - Instructional Development Fund (IDF), application and review notes April 1975 (Box 15)
  - Instructional Technology Committee, Commission on Education, Meeting Notes November 17, 1969 (Box 15)
  - International Congress on Technology Assessment (ISTA)
    - Conference List circa 1977 (Box 15)
    - General Files October 1976 (Box 15)